me
foree
fore
sir uh so we finished our description of
uh constructs uh this morning uh we
talked about identifying what constructs
were and we were talking about the
intern terms of the uh in terms of
changing things and although uh
constructs in general and constructs how
they are treated at this point in the
Sutra where the Buddha explains the
intent of his other sutras are slightly
different emphasis right they were
emphasizing certain kinds of constructs
this morning uh as opposed to constructs
in general but anyway you get a general
idea of what a construct is and we
Define constructs with regard to
changing things and then we can also
unchanging things this morning we were
both mostly doing it with changing
things but uh you you've seen how uh all
all phenomena whether it's uh changing
things or other things can be defined in
terms of the three groups or the three
attributes right uh meaning and uh what
do you call
uh
constructs uh changing things and
emptiness itself so you've seen how you
can uh you can
explain uh how those three groups apply
or can be derived from any single one of
those groups right uh and that's what we
went through this morning so we've been
through that and we're just about
finished with the constructs with the
idea of a
construct excuse me uh but uh you can
also apply that reasoning to all other
objects so you can Define in a sense uh
all all objects uh that way all three of
the groups can be described by using the
groups all three of the attributes can
be used can be described by all existing
phenomena can be described in the way we
did this morning for uh um constructs
with the three
groups
for
foree
so uh now we're getting on to a finer
distinction okay uh which is the fact
that uh a a stick or this stick in
particular is the object which is nam
stick okay the fact so that we have to
distinguish between its
being uh we have to distinguish between
the object of the of the word stick and
the fact that it is the object of the
word stick okay so distinguish between
the object of the word stick and this
being the object of the word stick in
tibetan there's a special grammar case
called D grammar case which means in
English we don't use it we say we
elected so and so president in tibetan
you have to say we elected so and so as
president and that's called Deni it's a
la it's a kind of a postposition in
tibetan grammar so uh in this case the
implication of that particular
postposition or grammar particle is that
there's a iction between uh the stick uh
the stick as the object uh that's called
stick and the fact that the stick is
called the stick okay and those are
distinctions so now don't forget that
we're talking about the fact that the
stick is the object called the stick
okay as opposed to the Sticks being the
object of of the name okay the fact the
stick not talking about the object of
the name stick we're talking talking
about the fact that the stick is the
thing called the stick that fact in
itself that condition in itself okay the
fact that the stick is called stick is
itself not something that comes from its
own side through any unique way of being
okay which is a way of saying it's not
something which
is it doesn't exist by definition it is
something which is created by our
concept that's a kind of kunda isn't it
okay the fact that the thing uh that
this is the thing which is named stick
is itself not something which is exists
by definition but rather it's something
which is in it in in its own way I
okay uh get this concept straight when
we talk about the fact that the stick is
the thing called the stick okay as
opposed to the thing called the stick
okay the the fact that the thing is
called a stick is going to be a sticking
point uh later on uh down below uh when
we when we get further on this is going
to be the subject of much discussion and
you have to make sure in your own mind
that you understand what we're talking
about when we say the fact that the
stick is called a stick or the fact that
the stick is the thing called the stick
okay the fact that the stick is the
thing called the stick the fact that the
stick is the thing which gets the name
stick
okay
for
uh so now J having gone we've gone
through a long explanation of what the
Sutra wherein the Buddha explains the
meaning of his sutras or the intention
of his trust uh we've gone we've been
dealing with this quotation the whole
conversation since this morning was
dealing with those three remember they
talked about three features they started
to talk about three features uh of that
arena in which the in which the mind
which makes constructs acts which is
changing things okay so remember that uh
the Sut was talking about that now
Jetson Kapa on the last line of page 22
is going to start analyzing that Sutra
quotation for us he's going to start
tearing apart the wording of that c
quotation for us we we finished talking
about the meaning of it now we're going
to see Jetson ca's take on it uh in his
own words he's finished up to the end of
line the last line of page 22 in the
middle there he has completed the Sut
quotation and now from the from the end
of line 22 he's be going to begin to
start tearing it down and the first
thing he says is uh the first three
terms he says are referring to the
object uh which the
conceptualizing or construction State of
Mind makes it constru makes it Con makes
its construction so talking about the
first three terms there are talking
about the arena in which uh or the basis
on which uh the constructing State of
Mind makes its constructs with regard to
changing things and those three terms
are if you remember uh it is the arena
in which uh concep uh construction
constructing state of mind uh acts it is
that thing which is uh has the
characteristics of being labeled both in
words and in and in thoughts and then
thirdly it has a quality of coming from
its causes and conditions right those
were the three terms so he says first of
all those three terms refer to what uh
the constructing or constructions are
directed towards which is changing
things then he draws a line he says now
from there on from that point on in the
Sutra Lord Buddha is explaining how it
is that the Mind applies
uh labels whether they are verbal or
mental onto these things so first we
talk about how uh changing things are
the object of of the imagining or the
labeling process construction process
and then after that he's going to talk
about how it actually works how they act
how the process of labeling both
mentally and verbally actually
functions
L uh we talked about all the crucial
points here this morning we covered in
great detail and and definitively we've
we've covered all the all the important
points here uh I just want to tie it
together with to tie it together for you
and uh relate everything to the actual
wording of the so the ideas we've
already covered now I just want to make
sure and J CLE wants to make sure that
you get the wording of the Sutra all
worked out to fit what we talked about
this
morning
for
uh so Thena goes on line uh page 23 line
two he has promised to give you the way
in which the labeling he's promised to
describe the way in which the labeling
process works both through words and
thoughts and and so now he's got down to
remember we took the back scratcher
stick and we took the boy Nam Tashi but
Buddha is going to take uh form or what
we call physical matter so in this case
the now the word Suk is being used uh in
the sense of the scanda or the part of a
person called Suk meaning physical
matter okay physical matter so the
Buddha is taking physical matter and
then he is examining it to see how we
draw constructs from both the main
object and from the characteristics of
the object remember so from the from the
object as a whole or from the object uh
the the main nature of the object and
then how do we draw constructs or how do
we create constructs based on the
characteristics of the whole and then uh
in tibetan we use two different words
here uh chat uh which is tricky word
okay which here means uh the particulars
of the uh the particulars of the object
and then he's going to discuss the kear
which means uh the uh features of the
object so he's using particulars and
features as almost synonymous here so
he's using jeta saying we're we're going
to discuss the the particulars meaning
the features how those act as a basis
for the construction constructing State
of Mind okay
and and then JSA promises to discuss it
in detail he says ship he means I'm
going to discuss this in great detail
and G says it's very important that he
says that because this is one of the
most important points of all the mind
only schools beliefs so Jessa is
promising us that he will cover it it
shipu means in great detail Because he
believes and he understands that this is
a very important part for us to
concentrate
on
that's uh we've talked about constructs
in great detail this morning case is
closed okay just is later going to go
into this detail but right now case is
closed you can you can shut that in
tobet say you can push it up now meaning
case is closed right now okay
nothing
for
uh so now we're going on to how to
identify or how to describe or how to
characterize that category that group
called changing things Shen right so now
we've gone on to that one we're we're
putting away uh constructs for a while
and now we're moving on to changing
things or shenan okay and then J Gish
says you know shenan is not such a
problem Shan by comparison Shang is a
lot easier you know this is a no-brainer
okay uh so he goes on and he starts
quoting uh that Sutra again the Sutra in
which the Buddha explains his sutras and
he says um Shen Wang has these changing
things have these three same
characteristics the SE three same
features that we talked about before
first of all it is the arena in which
the constructing State of Mind is doing
its thing it's functioning secondly it
does have a quality of being labeled in
different ways both by words and and by
your mind and then thirdly it is a it
has a quality or a condition of being
something which grows from its causes
and conditions so now we're treating
changing things Shen wangs not with
regard to being the focus or the lo you
know the locus or the or or we're not
talking about them in terms of how they
act as what the constructing state of
mind or KS refer to or apply to because
we're not explaining KS anymore we're
not talking about uh anymore about
constructs now we're treating Shong on
their own okay not so much as not so
much uh as as having a relationship to
uh constructs but but on their but from
their own side as as Shen Wongs as
changing things they also exhibit the
same three qualities that we talked
about the same three features that we
talked about with when we were talking
about them as relating to
uh constructs so now they're like
shenans get to stand on their own and
have the same three qualities but not so
much emphasis on with relation to
constructs so this now the Sutra is
talking about these three features as
they relate to uh changing things on
their own standing on their own
okay uh this is easy to see how these
three features again apply to changing
things it's pretty much we' covered
already so I'm not going to go into much
detail on it's not a big
thing
uh now he's going to J Kaa quotes the
Sut right he quotes the just the Sut
goes into those three features with
regard to changing things and now the
Sut runs out on page uh I'm sorry on
line eight right in the middle of line 8
page 23 there's the end of the Su
quotation the Su quotation was only two
and a half lines right and all it said
was uh changing things are the arena of
the constructs uh changing things are
the uh have the characteristic of being
the the uh something like the the thing
labeled and changing things have a
quality of being uh produced or or
having to do with production of things
so then jetona says look that's all the
Sutra says about them it's easy and now
I'll give you a short uh a short
description of what those three features
refer to when they're talking about
changing things and that short
description starts on line eight in the
Middle where it says Tong okay and what
it means is the first one meaning the
the first of the three features with
regard to changing things alone and not
so much emphasizing the relationship to
uh constructs the first one refers to
the fact that uh is is demonstrating
says Jetson kaapa whose object they are
who it is that's focusing upon them who
is that uh the constructing state of
mind right and then secondly uh the
second term is describing how they are
the thing which receives the label of
the constructing state of mind and the
third one is simply indicating their
basic nature what is their basic nature
they are products of their of their
causes and results uh causes and
conditions so that that completes uh
Jena take on what those three features
mean with regard to changing
things
nothing uh changing things is a short
story finished close the case nothing
more to say much about it let's go
on
fore
uh given that you understand construct
so well that now that we move on to the
third Group which is totality or The
Emptiness of things it's just a breeze
for you now uh because you realize that
it's just defined in terms of what's
denied when we speak of emptiness so you
since you know that so well now it's
just a a breeze uh 96 up from the bottom
uh page
23 uh they start quoting the Sutra on
what how those three features refer to
things which are EMP emptiness itself
right emptiness itself so here we
go the trick here is the is the
expression meaning the thusness or that
Berry and that Berry is like a is a word
for emptiness so that Berry
uh that very thing uh which involves
again the same three characteristics
okay which is tied up into those things
which are the object of uh constructs uh
those things which uh display uh the
characteristics of labeling uh those
things which uh have to do with uh the
process of production but the Deni means
the very nature of those things right so
now that he's added he's added Nest to
all those three features right uh that
is uh the ultimate nature of uh that is
the that is totality or emptiness with
regard to things which are labeled or
things which are the objects of
constructs okay uh and uh when we talk
about their nature or their very nature
now he's using the word very
nature um the impossibility the very
impossibility of their nature meaning
their emptiness okay uh here the wording
is the very impossibility of their
nature uh the very in fact the very fact
or the impossibility of their self-
nature says he says uh that is the that
that very nature now we're on the second
line from the bottom page 23 is the
object on which total Purity rests and
now you know uh from the other day that
total Purity refers to the path of total
Purity meaning a code word for the
direct perception of emptiness so so
that that thing which you can describe
in all those ways says the Sutra that's
uh the thing which is which is the
attribute called uh totality meaning
emptiness okay so that's that's the
Sutra presentation of how we describe
totality or emptiness the the third
group or the third attribute in the
minomi
school
fore
uh now we have a little more subtle now
remember from this morning take that
those three things right and we got the
stick over here right we got the kak
here right uh but now it's going to be a
little bit different so here you got the
stick and uh now we're not now we're
talking about a new idea the fact that
the stick is the thing called the stick
okay which is a kak in itself okay which
is a which is a construct in itself the
fact that the stick is the thing that's
called the
stick the fact that that fact doesn't
come of its own accord doesn't exist by
definition is another way of studying
the sticks Yong the The Emptiness of the
stick I'll say it again here you got the
stick here you got the fact that the
stick is what we call the stick and the
fact that the fact that that the stick
is what we call the stick is not in
itself something that exists by
definition is the emptiness or is the
young group in this case is the totality
one more time here's the stick the fact
that the stick is called the stick
itself is not a fact that exists by
definition and that fact is the
emptiness uh in this case Okay is the
totality or The Emptiness in this case
okay that's how we describe uh that
third attribute uh in the Min in the
minor
SK
for
okay this is tough uh take the fact that
the stick is what we call the stick okay
uh if if that existed uh take that fact
as something which as if it did Exist by
definition okay if that fact that fact
viewed as if it was something that did
Exist by definition is the gcha in this
case it is what we deny okay it is what
Emptiness is empty of okay I'll do it
one more time uh the fact that the fact
that this stick is what is called the
stick if if that fact existed by
definition you know viewed from the
point of view as if it did Exist by
definition that's an impossible thing
right but if it did Exist by definition
if there were such a thing that's what
we are denying we were denying that
possibility and when we successfully
deny that g
a fact that the pen uh is what we call
the pen that existed by definition which
is impossible right uh once we cancel
that once we disprove that uh once we
show that that's impossible then we
arrive at emptiness uh that's yungu okay
that's what we call totality we arrive
at at emptiness through that process by
denying uh the fact that the fact that
the pen is what we call the pen could
Exist by definition when we deny that we
arrive at totality or emptiness as it's
taught in the mind only school okay got
it
yeah
uh yeah that's the real case it it
really doesn't yeah it doesn't exist by
definition them yeah yeah you can use
both uh that is what we call the the
lack of a self to objects okay and in
the mind only School uh Chon's right I
left out that last piece there uh in the
mind only
school this is the lack of a self to
objects which is the ultimate the
highest form of emptiness to them okay
this is the highest form of emptiness
the lack of self-existence to objects
and remember that in this case objects
refers to the parts of a person as
opposed to the person which in in this
school is a higher or is the ultimate
form of emptiness okay The Emptiness of
objects what is that it's the fact that
the fact that the pen is what we call
the pen is the is is the thing that's
called the pen uh doesn't exist by
definition okay okay or if you want to
State it even better the fact that the
fact that the pen is what we call the
pen uh which could Exist by definition
doesn't exist is uh is is Yong okay and
if there were such a fact that would be
uh the ultimate self nature
self-existent thing okay and the and the
canceling of that is emptiness ultimate
emptiness
for
uh he thinks that you were talking about
something you weren't talking about but
still interesting okay so uh he says
probably he's thinking probably he's
thinking in his mind why are we just
talking about the lack of self- nature
to things and we haven't mentioned the
lack of self- nature of a person because
lack of self- nature is always divided
into two kinds the lack of self- nature
to Winston and the lack of self- nature
of Winston's Parts which is called the
lack of self- nature of things or the
lack of self- nature of of objects so
when you think about the construct if
you take this morning's class and you
think about the construct that we said
didn't exist right uh the construct the
idea that the construct existed by by
definition that was the the construct
that didn't exist and or or if you take
the the example we just gave of of
something uh the fact that the pen is
what we call the pen the fact that that
fact uh doesn't uh have any uh nature of
existing by definition that that if
there were a fact like that that could
Exist by definition that that would be
the lack of that would be a self nature
of things and the lack of that or the
general absence of that is the no self
nature of things uh so really what
that's one kind of goar right that's one
kind of thing that we deny what the fact
that the we deny that the fact that the
pen is what you call the pen exists by
definition
and a a a fact that the pen is called
the pen that did Exist by definition
which is impossible right that would be
one kind ofra that would be one kind of
thing that Emptiness is empty of and if
once you cancel that kind of self-
nature you arrive at what we call the
self- nature of things now what is it
that you cancel to arrive at the self-
nature of a person you see CU that would
be a different GTA that's a slightly
different GTA and then he's quick to
point out that it's hard to draw
distinctions between the two go cuz
neither one of them exists right they're
both just theortical things that don't
really exist okay but uh there says
there are two schools of thought about
the the second goo or the second thing
that emptiness denies that when we talk
about the emptiness of a person like The
Emptiness of Winston for example then
there's a there's a certain kind of uh
gaka okay there's a certain kind of
self-existing person that we're thinking
of and and then when you cancel that
self-existence or you prove the General
lack of that self-existence you arrive
at The Emptiness of the person right and
that there are two schools of thought
says some people say that that is a kind
of Yung do some people describe that as
oh that's Yung do that's totality that
is emptiness in the middle way school
I'm sorry in the mind only school but
then there are other people who say
that's just a kind of tot you can call
that a kind of totality but they're kind
of implying that it's not a kind of Yung
okay so there's some people who say that
uh the lack the general lack of a of a
to put it simply a self-existent self is
only a kind of Y dup and not really y
dup it's just that y dup which is a lack
of something of a self-existing
person and they describe it that way and
some people just go straight for Yong
say yeah that's a Yong so there are two
schools of thought about that one about
that kind of uh lack of
self-existence
for
uh either way uh all there there are
different schools of thought some very
great Buddhist philosophers have said
that um the general lack of a self-
nature to the person of a person is
itself young group itself is totality is
emptiness is the third group of
emptiness and other great schol have
come along and said no that's not that's
just a kind of totality which is
represented by the lack of uh
self-existent person but implying that
it's not real totality it's not really
the The Emptiness that's described by
the mind only school and he says uh
obviously but everybody agrees that
there's kind some kind of distinctions
have to be made here because you do have
a lack of self- nature to things or
parts of a person and then you have a
lack of self nature of a person and the
the opposite of a self-existing person
uh can be discussed as being yup or
totality or emptiness in the mind only
school or it can be described as just
something that you call uh Yung dup or
emptiness in the in the terms of the
minol school uh so everybody agrees that
there's some kind of Distinction to be
made here now whether you go side with
one side or whether you side with the
other side still there's going to be a
discussion coming later in this very
book that talks about the lack what you
get after you cancel a self-existent
person you know what kind of emptiness
do you get out of that and interestingly
enough that's going to come in our
discussion later of the first turning of
the wheel remember we've been bogged
down here we've been tied up here in the
second turning of the wheel everything
we've said for a while has been with
regard to the second turning of the
wheel later on we're going to start
talking about the first turning of the
wheel and this same question is going to
come back to haunt us later so we'll
we'll treat it
then
uh this morning we were discussing a
kind of construct that didn't exist
weren't we okay we were describing a
kind of construct that didn't exist and
we have a name that we're going to call
it and then then gisha says he pauses
and he says you know it's kind of hard
to name things that don't exist
meaningfully you know meaningfully how
do you name a thing that doesn't exist
but you know in terms of talking about
it in terms of having to discuss it we
will call it the self nature of objects
or the self- nature of the parts of a
person okay the a quote I think in
English you have to say a quote uh self-
nature it's like the purple elephant
right it mean
you have to say I think in English you
have to say a socalled self- nature of
objects
okay of objects meaning when we say
objects here it's a code word for parts
of a person as opposed to the
person uh
that same thing
same sir get
there
uh yesterday loen asked me about uh you
know to help translate into English well
how do we translate Yong you know Yung
that third group or that third attribute
you know how how do we going to talk
about it and then I open the door to ma
Mika we went in there and I explained it
in terms of the minute a thing exists
dup then everything about it y uh is is
empty okay like all the parts of it
everything about it the thing itself as
soon as it exists everything about it is
empty dup Yong Yong dup okay but then he
says you know there's another way you
can describe it and that's if you take
the word dup as as as referring to all
existing objects so if you draw a big
line around uh every existing object in
the world which is called dup right dup
also means to exist okay so if you draw
a huge line around every existing object
in the world then a top each object
laying upon each object in their
totality y uh is emptiness okay so the
whole totality of every object in the
world each member of that totality has
its own emptiness and in that sense
total existence you see upon uh every
existing every existing group object in
totality y has emptiness okay in uh
emptiness applies to every single object
there
totally in totality okay so uh that's
another way of describing Yong
uh as a word and not in the meaning
right I mean it helps I mean that's has
some meaning but the main point is if
you're trying to struggle in English
with the words Yong and dup uh this is
helpful
okay
don't forget that when I give a a uh
what do you call it an eological
explanation of a word we are not talking
necessarily that the result of that
eological explanation will be a term
which is totally correct or totally
accurate or totally inclusive we if you
do that with eological explanations you
might get into trouble later with some
of them so they are Des descriptive and
not comprehensive
okay
uh so just to review just to review
where we are don't forget that this is
how we describe Yong dup or what are we
going to call it now uh let's stick to
to what were we calling it before
totality totality what was the other
Oneal what was the let's say totality
let's stick with totality okay so if you
take uh
totality what is it again with reference
to a water picture how do you describe
it describe it with reference to a water
picture we are discussing the fact that
the water piter is the object or the
thing which is named water piter okay
the fact that that the water piter is
the thing that's named water
piter the fact that that fact itself
doesn't exist by definition is the Y grp
of the water picture okay it is the
emptiness of the water pcture that's
what we call the totality of the water
pcture okay and so canceling any fact
that the picture is what we call the
water picture that could have existed by
definition is how we arrive that the
emptiness or the Yung Dro or the
totality of the water piter you guys got
all that right you guys got all that
straight uh now somebody's going to come
along and cause a problem with that
somebody's going to come along and have
a misconception about it uh the
omnicient Jon Jon he's back again he's
back again he's got a problem with that
okay he's got a problem with that way of
explaining it he's got a he's got a
problem with jppa saying that that's how
the S is explaining it
okay
fore
uh J Kaba is addressing a contradiction
that Jon's beliefs incur right so Jon
has expressed the believe that um Yong
or emptiness in the idea of the my only
school
is the absence of the other
two okay so anything which doesn't
anything which is uh devoid of uh of
constructs or anything which is devoid
of being uh a changing thing that's what
yup is okay yondo is not the absence of
a self-existent thing yup is the absence
of the other two groups
okay okay uh and that's how he defines
uh young that's how he defines emptiness
okay and that's how he says the minority
School defines emptiness and then jetuka
comes up to him and says uh I I I don't
quite remember did you say that uh this
Sutra in which the Buddha explained what
he really meant in his sutras did you
say that was something he were supposed
to take figurative or literally and then
Jon says well I said it was literal
right because he's a he's almost like a
mind only himself right he says you have
to take it literally okay and and then
Jetson compa says well then you
contradict the text directly because the
text doesn't say that at all the text
describes Yong dup or emptiness exactly
in the way I just described it nowhere
in the text does it describe it uh it
describes it as the lack of a
self-existent uh construct applying to
to to changing
things okay it doesn't describe it as a
lack of those two categories being y
okay got it uh it the text says the Sut
what's the Sut is really saying is that
a self-existent construct doesn't apply
to changing things whereas you're taking
it uh voidness or emptiness to be the
simple lack in things or simply
something that is uh a a a voidness or a
general lack of the other two groups and
you describe emptiness that way you
contradict the Sutra which you say has
to be taken literally yourself directly
okay
for
uh the the scriptural quotation and I'm
going to it's going to be a little more
clear now uh from what I understand but
it's difficult uh the scriptural backup
for this is on page
23 uh the third line from the bottom uh
and and J CA says look that line there
is saying that uh Emptiness is that
young DRP emptiness in the mind only
school is simply the lack it's the fact
that changing things do not have a
nature of having constructs which apply
to them which Exist by definition right
that's that's what it means but but Jon
has said is saying that the fact that uh
that emptiness doesn't have a nature of
being uh a changing thing nor a
construct uh that's his idea of of what
Emptiness is and jetona says if you say
it that way uh you contradict the Sutra
at this point where the Sutra itself
says that uh y emptiness is defined as
the general lack uh among changing
things of any nature of being a
construct who comes from its own which
exists by definition and it's not that
emptiness is described by the Buddha
being the the the general lack of a
characteristic of a quality of being a
changing thing or lack of being a
construct applied to to emptiness the
fact that Emptiness is not a changing
thing or the fact that uh emptiness is
not a construct is not the point of what
emptiness means that's not its emptiness
that's not what emptiness is and that's
not what the text says and you
contradict this very quotation 923 uh
third line from the
bottom yeah that's I got it
right J's Viewpoint is the general
absence uh the fact that Emptiness is is
not uh a changing thing or construct is
its emptiness that's what Emptiness is
is that that's his idea and it's wrong
okay
nothing and G repeats that what the Su
is really saying is that changing things
the lack the fact that changing things
don't possess any nature of of having uh
constructs the constructs that don't
exist right a construct that could Exist
by definition the fact that that kind of
construct could never apply to changing
things is Yung is emptiness and that's
what the scpt is really saying so J know
I got it
wrong
foree
uh he says you you described it
correctly this morning you describe it
correctly this morning you got into it
this morning you got into it this
morning you all were very close to the
same thing meaning what the fact that uh
dasi and the fact that Tashi is the
thing that we call
Tashi the the fact that the fact that
the thing that we got the fact that the
fact that Tashi is the thing we call
Tashi but that that doesn't exist by
definition and that and that t is not
that okay I'll do it again uh the fact
that the fact that Tashi is what we call
the name Tashi uh doesn't exist by
definition is the Y dup of Tashi okay is
the emptiness of Tashi you guys got it
you guys got this morning you got it you
got it you express it you express
everybody got it and that is what the
Sutra is saying that is what the Sutra
is is talking about now here comes J
Jona uh he's saying that uh he accepts
the wording of the Sutra literally and
then he goes on to say that that's not
what the Sut meant that the Sut meant
something else that Yong or emptiness is
the Gen is the fact that uh y uh that
emptiness is not a changing thing and
it's not a construct right and that
that's what emptiness is that's complete
g means that's a complete internal
direct contradiction you know he say on
one hand he says he believes the Sutra
literally and on the other hand he's
he's explaining it in a way that the Sut
never States and that that's that's a
direct contradiction
okay uh we better uh go over the wording
a little bit I you know like it's almost
like we don't have any choice but to go
over the wording a bit do we
okay
m
you
uh on page 24 towards the end the big
point that Jona is making he's trying to
go over the individual words of the
Sutra to help Jon understand the Sutra
right and he says you know the Sutra
says
itself twice Den means itself or its
very self or it's it's it's it's dness
or something like that in itself itself
uh is the word Deni and jokar is trying
to help Jano understand it more clearly
and he says now listen the Buddha said
itself twice uh when he said uh and by
the way in tibetan itself is also like
almost exclusive meaning only itself
okay there are those two flavors of the
word Deni in in tibetan so he says don't
forget that the Sutra said itself twice
the first time the Sutra says itself
they're talking about dependent things
or things which are caused and then the
second time it's is talking about itself
they're talking about constructs with
specific regard to the constructs which
don't have any uh existence okay so and
the whole thing comes out then in
English
right uh changing things themselves
meaning restrict yourself to this groom
changing things themselves uh do not the
fact that they do not
possess constructs that don't exist
themselves is the yungu is the emptiness
of those changing things okay I'll say
it one more time the way the S uses the
word themselves uh Jess was trying to
explain it to Jona uh changing things
themselves meaning as a group uh do not
possess uh any nature of being of having
applied to them constructs the kinds
that don't exist themelves and the the
the general lack of those kinds of
constructs themselves on
changing things themselves is what the
emptiness of those changing things is
the Y the totality of those changing
things is so J says you J have to
understand what those two D mean first
one referring to Shen Wang second one
referring to the contct that don't
exist
spe
uh if you want to go back to the Sutra
and find those two Denise right to
actually you know we lock on to them and
you can underline them and say oh well
he's the Denise that he's talking about
go to page 23 uh Fifth Line from the
bottom very last syllable in on the
fifth line is day and then the first
syllable on the sixth line is n then
that's the first then you go looking for
the second di it's the de in the third
line from the bottom of page 23 which is
a synonym in tibetan for Deni okay so
those are the two Denis the one is not
spelled like that but it's totally the
same meaning
okay uh better make a little Mark on
those Denise okay uh because later on
there might be a hassle come up about
those little denes uh if we have time
we'll see if we have time but we might
come back and revisit those two denies
and discuss an issue that comes up with
those denies okay
for
for yes sir I got a question for you
guys
the next section is called how things
are empty or you know how what does it
mean to be empty okay what does it mean
to be empty of something and he says now
think about normal everyday World normal
everyday speech and people go around and
they would describe this room for
example as being empty you know nobody's
in the room you open the door you look
in you say the room is empty that's one
way of thinking about the expression
empty okay but then you have a little
bit different flavor don't you if you
say
look at a a rope that someone has
mistaken for a snake right like that's
Dusk and it's a little bit dark and
somebody's mistaken this rope for a
snake and then suddenly they realize
it's not a snake at all it's just a rope
they are perceiving that this rope is
devoid of any nature of being a real
snake right it is empty of having any
nature of being a real snake it is
devoid uh so so in tibetan the word is
the same uh the room is is is
empty and then then that rope piece of
rope is empty of having any nature of
being a real snake okay or devoid of
being a snake so you have voidness right
or emptiness uh when you think about it
what do you guys think generally
speaking you know if you really think
about it carefully uh emptiness they are
both uh the same sort of idea right it's
the absence of something okay so
generally speaking it's a it's about the
same thing when you say the room is
empty and when you say the piece of rope
is empty of being a real snake or
something devoid of any nature of being
a real snake so very generally they both
mean some kind of absence or lack of
something but in your opinions now
asking you a question everybody in your
opinions in in everyday speech in the
everyday meaning of the word emptiness
are those two the same are they exactly
same or do they have a slightly
different flavor or
connotation
that's a
cha uh when somebody says the room is
empty what do they think about when when
they say the room is
empty
so when you come in and say the room is
empty the question is whether or not
there are people in that room whether or
not there is Furniture in that room it's
not a question of whether the guy is a
guy or the furniture is a Furniture
right now when you say a piece of rope
is devoid of having any nature of being
a real snake what do you mean then what
do you have in mind
then
intellectual
something having to do with nature of
being and not if it's presence or
absence how is it what is
it
yeah he agrees with you and he likes the
way you said it and he says yeah the
case with the piece of rope is that
you're looking at the piece of rope and
trying to decide your mind is it this
snake isn't it a snake could it be a
snake was it a snake you know like is it
going to bite me or not it's something
like a conversation going in your mind
you're trying to decide something
intellectual about the about the piece
of rope he says I kind of like that
part uh what was your question I
forgot or statement well just it's it's
a it's an
intellectual you're not trying to
determine whether not something that's
present or ABS what you're trying to
determine is the nature of what it is
okay do you agree what are you thinking
about is that yeah is
that are you all in agreement that those
that that's the main point I think
there's another point M there might be
something in the room there might not be
something in the room but the Rope like
never was a snake and never could
be
uh philosophically you're correct but
remember I phrased this question in
terms of what are guys to say in the
normal everyday world you know and they
don't come in and say well you know uh
there's a word in tibetan which is uh
adventitious you see I mean some kind of
philosophical word you know is the the
absence of presence of a chair is
something we call adventitious mean in
philosophy meaning you know it was like
that and then it changed into something
else but this is what we call you know
ontologically you know it wasn't a it
couldn't it never was a snake and and
couldn't have been a snake and never
will be a snake and he says oh yeah yeah
we don't have to use that kind of
language here we're just the guys we're
just walking in the room and I kind of
like the way they said it and you so
don't forget that I phrase my question
in in the way that normal people would
think of the difference between those
two things and really it is a question
you know you can say it in Tibet and the
way I said it to him was was one is a
question of Y one is a question of Y see
in Tibet in the word is or to be has two
flavors one is the presence or absence
one is the identity is it or is it not
that thing you see I mean and and he
likes Chon's way of expressing
it uh when we say that dependent objects
meaning changing things are devoid of
any nature of construct of the type that
doesn't exist right uh the construct
that is existing by definition right
when we say that changing things like
the boy Dashi is devoid or absent of
those things we are of course referring
to the second kind of emptiness the way
we used emptiness with regard to the
piece of rope and the snake the Rope is
devoid or or doesn't have any nature of
being a real snake and we are not using
the word empty in the sense that we use
it in the in in the sense of in the
world when we say the room is empty okay
so we're really talking about in terms
of identity that the thing is devoid of
having that nature rather than uh the in
the way that in the everyday world we
use the world the word empty to describe
a
room no sir
for
uh and now we get you know this is his
pattern of G giving you the meaning of
it uh with an easy to understand example
and then taking you back to jessa's word
and say that's what he's trying to say
here okay so now you get back to the
wording third line from the bottom on
page 24 and jeta says now how is it that
things are empty it's not emptiness in
the sense of a of a water picture being
here or not being here in front of us
okay that's not what we mean by the word
emptiness in this case what we're
referring to here says Jenson Kaa is the
emptiness of uh what you say the the the
fact that a person doesn't have any what
we call material existence now we didn't
get to that point yet we didn't discuss
that thing yet what it means to have uh
material existence in tibetan it's Z
okay uh to exist to have any uh let's
talk we'll call it material existence
right now okay U that's the kind of that
that kind of identity emptiness and uh G
says for now think of it as the fact
that uh changing things do not have any
nature of the the constructs which
didn't exist okay their lack of having
any constructs apply to them of the kind
that don't exist is their is their
emptiness and that's a different kind of
emptiness uh than the one that's that's
described by saying uh oh there's no
water picture here on the floor in front
of us okay that would be the equivalent
of what Gesa was speaking about when you
talk about the room being empty and then
when you talk about the person not
having any material existence
or you talk about changing things not
being such that concepts of the kind
that don't constructs of the kind that
don't exist uh don't apply to them uh
that's referring to the G's example
about the piece of rope and the snake
that the piece of rope is devoid of
having any nature of being a real snake
so so there are the correlations
there
for
uh now on page 25 we reached page 25 the
second line and uh this is where J Kaa
says well actually where the CIT says
who is it no it's just Kaa uh this is
where he says when we talk about
emptiness in terms of it being uh
changing things not
possessing uh constructs that apply to
them of the kind that don't exist right
that exist by definition right uh that's
the kind of constructs we're talking
about the ones that refer to changing
things and the ones that don't exist
right uh those are the kind of
constructs we're talking about and we're
not going to be talking about and the
Sutra does not emphasize the other kinds
of constructs such as uh empty space or
uh archetypes or things like that uh
it's not talking about that kind uh
again uh gisha reminds you remember we
skipped ahead to this section earlier
this morning and this was a section
where Jona says look the Sutra is not
emphasizing laying any emphasis not
making any great mention of those other
kinds of constructs it is emphasizing or
talking about the kind of constructs
with regard to Chang in things that
don't exist or do exist but it's talking
about constructs with regard to changing
things because it's through those
examining those constructs that you can
come easily to an understanding of
emptiness because emptiness means the
fact that changing things are devoid of
certain kinds of those constructs
okay
foree you have
another
I can add one more thing here while
there's a pause uh he said uh when he
said that these are the kind of uh
constructs that we were talking about
the constructs involving the very nature
of things and the constructs involving
the features of things and he mentioned
that
also by the way please have your tapes
ready okay like ready to pull out okay
all
right
for
uh jeta on page 25 on line three
mentions at the two points in the text
at the two points in the text it's
called Kik okay and then Gish being the
thorough person he is says I want to
find these two points in the text well
one of them is back on page
nine uh the uh the third line from the
bottom where it
says
that's the first occasion that they're
talking
about
uh the second occasion that jop is
referring to appears on page
22 uh it's introduced seven lines from
the top where it says Su number three
and then uh he says you may Wonder
yourself blah blah blah what this is all
talking about and then he goes into a
quotation from the Su that is the second
occasion so those are the two occasions
mentioned in page 25 line three where J
talks about two
occasions uh then again they mentioned
here uh uh construct what
say uh constructs which are the
result constructing constructs that
relate to the nature of the general
thing and then constructing constructs
that relate to the characteristics of
the thing right constructing constructs
of the nature and constructing
constructs of the features of the object
okay uh we're talking about those two
kinds of constructs uh constructs
constructed about the nature or the main
thing object and then construct
constructed about the features of the
thing as opposed to the main thing
uh those are the two kinds of constructs
we're going to be talking about and not
uh the other ones like empty space or
archetypes or things like
that uh remember that jenta said I'll
explain why we only deal with these
kinds of constructs later on and don't
forget that this morning we jumped way
ahead and J CA explained why those
constructs were more useful than to work
with than the other General constructs
that was because it helped us to achieve
understand Yung dup or emptiness
right uh you remember I went to page 85
this morning and helped you out with
that and and that was the backup uh or
that was where uh jetaa explained again
starting with the uh on starting from
the seventh line on page
uh and and in that quotation again it
says uh why is it that uh in the U uh in
the why is the in generally speaking
it's true that there are a lot of
different constructs in the world says
Genta including archetypes and including
empty space itself Etc but why does uh
the Sutra not refer to these uh
different these more General kinds of uh
constructs well because it doesn't it's
not a necessary
uh in understanding right in
understanding what it is that makes
emptiness empty you see what it what it
is that Emptiness is empty of which is
those constructs which Exist by
definition you see I mean or those
constructs that that relate to those
particular changing objects so those are
the constructs we have to talk about
that's why the Sutra talks about those
constructs and doesn't talked about
those other more General constructs it's
talking about constructs with regard to
changing things because it's the ABS of
those that helps us understand emptiness
as emptiness relates to changing
things I told you about all that this
morning
for
uh I talked this morning all about this
guy named Tashi this boy named Tashi
Tashi was going Tashi went you know we
got Tashi we got Tashi down we got Tashi
down so now that you got Dashi down you
understand how those three attributes of
the Mind only school appli to the first
example he gave we were giving Tashi as
an example the scripture is giving uh
physical man now he's changing by the
way from Vis visual man which is one
interpretation of Suk to uh the first of
the five heapes which is your physical
body or physical matter in general okay
so now having
understood how those three attributes
apply to a thing called physical matter
right which is what everything we've
done with Tashi Tashi Tashi Tashi okay
you got it down with Tashi says Lord
Buddha now just apply that to everything
else in the universe okay take that
explanation of how the three groups
apply to a thing like physical matter
and then you can go apply that to all
the other objects in the universe in
fact you could go back to the first
turning of the wheel you could go back
to everything else mentioned in the
first turn the wheel and apply it one by
one to all the things mentioned there
for example it says here to the
remaining four heaps to the remaining
four parts of a person which as you know
are discrimination feeling other factors
and Consciousness uh you can apply it to
those as well you can first you can
apply it to that then you can go ahead
and apply it to the 12 uh Gates of the
senses okay then you can go ahead and
apply it to the 12 lengths of dependent
generation then you could go ahead and
apply it to to the four kinds of
sustenance and then you could go ahead
and apply it to the six categories and
then you could go ahead and apply it to
the 18 if you want six or 18 uh
categories doesn't matter take each one
take each one of them one by one and you
can take those three attributes that we
talked about which are
uh constructs uh changing things or
dependent things and yr or emptiness
totality and you can apply each of each
of the three has an application with
every single object mentioned in that
list I just gave you okay which is the
content which is the subject matter of
the first turning of the wheel not not
that how those three apply them but
those you know describing all of those
objects in themselves is the subject
matter of the first turning the wheel so
you can go back to the first turn of the
wheel take all that stuff that Lord
Buddha talked about and then examine how
each one of those objects individually
uh how they they all how the three
groups can apply to each one
individually and then you're done you're
set okay once you understand it with
that guy Tash that's been walking around
okay
nothing
for
uh don't forget that uh with those ones
that we've mentioned just now the the
five heaps the 12 doors of sense the 12
parts of depend generation Links of
depend regation the four kinds of
sustenance and and the categories
whether you describe them as 6 or 18
with that we've only covered five of the
seven subjects in the first turning of
the wheel we still have the four arot
truth and after that we have the
37 uh components of uh
Enlightenment and and how does it relate
to those now how can we apply that those
same three groups to those oh yeah you
can here he goes jeta page 25 uh eight
lines eight lines from the bottom and he
begins to talk about how the three
groups relate to the first of the four
ARA truths so this is how do the three
groups relate to the ARA truth of
suffering okay uh you can have a you can
have the noble I'm sorry a truth of
suffering and you can be focusing on it
right it's a it's a changing thing or a
dependent thing and you can be examining
it uh how you conceptualize of it in a
general way and how you conceptualize of
its characteristics right which is you
know having a construct about it as a
whole and then having a construct about
one of its features right so here's an
example when you look at the AR truth of
suffering and you say this is the AR
truth of suffering then you are having a
construct about it uh which is regards
its whole which is regarding the whole
truth in itself and then when you go
ahead and say uh which the Buddha said
the big quality or the big feature of
the AR truth of suffering is that it's
something you have to figure out that is
happening to you y means your
relationship to the first AR of Truth is
supposed to be that just figure out that
that's who you are that that that you
are suffering just to figure that out is
a big achievement you know so the Buddha
said what should your relationship be to
the first of the ARA truths just to
realize you're having it okay uh when
you look at the first ar your truth and
you think about it this is something I'm
supposed to realize is happening to me
then you are having a construct about a
feature of the first St of Truth so
there's a case where you have a
construct about the first di tooth in
general and you're also having a
construct about the a feature of the
first di tooth which is the feature that
you better figure out that it's
happening to you okay so that's an
example of uh uh of a of a construct
through words and thoughts uh which is
regarding uh the first of the AR truth
then he says you can go on and describe
that with all the other with all the
other a your truths you can go on and
describe the when why about the other uh
a your truths let me see I left that one
thing uh yeah and not only is it true of
how Concepts apply to the first IR truth
but you can also apply uh think about
how the quality of those three
features
uh
nothing nothing uh so with that we've
described how constructs apply to the
first di truth both towards the first di
truth as a whole and towards the first
di of Truth as we focus on one of its
characteristics which in this case was
you better figure out it's happening to
you okay but what is how does the second
grouping meaning shenwan meaning uh the
fact that things are you know the cause
things how does cause things relate to
the first St of Truth very simple they
are
causeing and that is the Shen Wang of
the first di of Truth you see uh the
very fact that the first ey of Truth is
a changing thing is how the first ey
truth possesses a quality of being
shenan okay so the first attribute
applies because you can say the first
truth this is the first AR truth the
second attribute applies because the
first AR truth is a changing thing and
the third attribute applies because uh
the thing the the quality of the
construct about it that doesn't
exist doesn't exist with regard to it is
its Y is is the emptiness of the first
di truth so you've got how the how
constructs relate to the first di of
Truth you finished how the fact that
it's a changing thing relates to the
first di truth and you've got how
emptiness relates to the first di truth
again all three attributes are all three
groups how they apply to the first di
truth once you get it with the first
Dion truth you get it with the rest of
the AUD truths and then you can go on to
explain the 37 qualities of
enlightenment in the same way and you've
covered the subject matter at the first
turning of the
wheel uh when I went through those three
things and we were covering them with
the kid Tashi and everything like that
and we got finished and I said to you do
you guys agree that the same reasoning
could be applied to every other object
in the universe and you said sure
everybody said sure
so here it is you know we're doing it
and they're covering every object there
is and uh it's the same
thing
fore
for
uh Gish went he had two expl
explanations here first he started out
by saying you know with regard to that
last page page 25 there in that whole
area in that whole section there have
been different ways of explaining it
okay different ways of explain what
Jetson Kaa meant and there have grown up
different uh very very great Masters
have expressed different opinions about
how to interpret these last few pages
and this whole section that we've been
on uh for example in the different
textbooks of the different monasteries
you'll find slightly different
explanations of those two pages and
there'll be a little bit of some issues
arising in this area and then he kind of
rested that and then he went on to say
by the way let's go back to page let's
go on to page 26 uh this is a wrap-up d
means this is a wrap-up okay you're
getting a wrap-up by uh Lord Buddha and
by Jona here on all the points that have
come up to here don't forget where we
started from we had the the bodh
SATA has come to the Buddha and said you
know Buddha you gave this first turning
of the wheel and then you gave a second
turning of the wheel and in the first
turn of the wheel you said certain
things and then in the second turn of
the wheel you turned around and said
nothing has any existence by existence
by definition and then I I came up to
you and I said you know Lord Buddha it's
kind of seems like you're contradicting
yourself possibly
or I don't understand what you had in
mind when at during the second turn of
the wheel you went on and said nothing
exists by definition uh when you had
just said you you'd kind of implied that
it did in the first turn of the wheel
what did you mean when you said nothing
existed by definition and then the mind
only school has been saying well uh
they've been quoting uh this this same
Sutra in the same Sutra Lord Buddha says
you
know you know what I had in mind I was
thinking of these three attributes or
these three groups and I was thinking
that each of the three can apply to
every existing object so when I said uh
things don't have any this nature things
don't have this nature things don't have
this nature I was thinking of those
three groups or those three attributes
meaning uh uh constructs uh things which
depend on others and and totality right
in the sense of emptiness uh I was
thinking of those three groups that's
what I had in mind when I said that
things didn't exist by Nature and and
that's what I was talking about I've
clarified for you what each of those
groups mean and most importantly I've
demonstrated to you how each of those
three groups applies to every single
existing object in the world every
single existing object in the world can
be described uh as having some
attributes of those all all three
attributes okay every existing object in
the world can be described in terms of
of those three attributes applying to
them and that's what I had in mind of
bodhak and dandak now is is replying to
the Buddhist response okay he asked a
question Buddha responded and now on
page 26 in the first half uh the Buddha
is dunam yak is replying to the Buddha
and he says I got it thank you very much
okay now I you know you explain to me
what you meant during the second turn of
the wheel and you said that that that's
not really what I meant not literally
what I meant was this thing about these
three groups and these three kinds of LA
of Nature and that's what I meant thank
you very much I understand what you're
saying um we have finished one major
section uh we're going on to the fourth
fourth major division uh you know I did
mention this little issue that came up
with the difference between the
textbooks of the different monasteries
on a certain point in the last few pages
uh let's get to that tomorrow we'll
cover that tomorrow okay I'm not going
to try to do it today we'll go we'll go
on to that tomorrow but now we've
reached a whole different
section uh don't forget I told you to
make some marks on your you know write
some stars at different places that's
where the problems lie uh I'm not going
to get into today you don't have to turn
to it right now uh we'll cover that
tomorrow we'll get to that tomorrow
case is closed new case is closed now we
go on to a new
section
for
m
uh we're about to go on a new section uh
if I tried to go into any detail on it I
would be interrupted by this irritating
little voice clock uh so all I can do is
give you a uh I'll give you a quick
rough out of what we're going to hit in
this section okay uh this section is
called drupon dupon means uh it's a
difficult word in tibetan I've had
trouble with it before but what he he
describes it very nice gisha describes
it very well it's dupon means uh the res
almost like a profit resulting from a
transaction so there's been a give and
take uh there's been uh uh an exchange
going on and due to those different
transactions doing due to all that
exchange uh some kind of conclusion some
kind of result some kind of profit is
going going to uh to be an outcome you
can call it like an outcome of the
exchange what is the exchange uh
that has presented a question to the
Buddha what did you mean when you said
this in the second turn of wheel and
then you turned around and said I'm
sorry you said this in the first
turnning of the wheel and then you
turned around and said this in the
second turning of the wheel what was
your what were you talking about and
then the Buddha has given an answer and
uhak listened to it and Paka said okay I
got it and the whole outcome the some
kind of outcome or conclusion to be
reached from The Exchange and that's the
subject of this section what kind of
outcome or what kind of conclusion has
been has been produced by this exchange
between the Lord Buddha and his disciple
well uh because Lord Buddha has been
speaking with language where he kept
saying you know what I really had in
mind or you know what I meant to say or
what I was really thinking of all during
that because he's using language like
that one immediate outcome is that we
understand that the first and second
turnings of the wheel are not to be
taken literally okay so one automatic
outcome is that oh uh because the Buddha
has been using this kind of language you
know what I really had in mind or what I
meant to say uh you know what I wanted
you to understand uh because he's been
using that kind of language about the
first two turnings of the wheel then we
can say that in the mind only School the
first two turnings of the wheel are
considered to be figurative spoken
figuratively and not to be taken
literally but you know this whole
exchange is the third turning of the
wheel okay uh this bodh sta going to the
Buddha and saying what did you mean when
you say that and the Buddha saying hey
here's what I meant in the first two
turnings of the wheel that is the third
turning of the wheel that exchange
itself is the third Turney of the wheel
now that exchange where the Buddha seems
to be burying his soul you know and
saying okay here's what I really meant
you know and this is what I really
intended to say now that seems to be
something we can take literally because
now the Buddhist seems to be speaking in
absolute terms in totally literal terms
you know he's saying you know what I
really had in mind to to tell you from
my heart yand this is what I really had
in mind and and then the Buddha speaking
in that sort of Frank honest you know
this is what I really had in mind's
terms then we can take the third turning
of the wheel another outcome of the
exchange another profit from all the
transactions is that we can come to
realize that the third turning of the
wheel according to this school is
something literal and and that's a rough
out of this section for you guys which I
can't uh you know I'm not going to
smooth it out now because the thing's
going to go off
okay
no uh so suppose somebody comes up to
you someday and says what was the third
turning of the wheel okay and you'll be
all ready to give a great answer you
know you'll say well you know there was
this and uh until he asks his question
until the moment that he asked his
question a third turning of the wheel
has not yet occurred you see
and then there comes this
buddh and he says oh Lord Buddha you
know what what about this I'm having
trouble with this idea and then the
Buddha comes and gives his answers you
know if they were writing a book at the
time if they had both been writers then
it would have been about 10 pages of
questions written by dandak and then
maybe 20 pages of Answers by Lord Buddha
and we would have taken those 30 pages
of trans you know of conversation and
that would have been a book called third
turning of the wheel you know so when
you think about if someone comes up to
you and says what is the third turning
of the wheel you got to say oh that's
when that body St asked those questions
and Lord Buddha gave those answers and
that's what the third turn of the wheel
is
pull down when I said uh if they had
been writers and if they had been
writing it down at the time uh the bod
office questions would have taken about
10 pages and the Buddhist answers maybe
20 pages and anwers reply and then said
that the the third of the wheel is 30
pages I'm not I don't want you to take
that literally okay you know I'm not
saying you know the third turn wheel is
30 little pages and that's all there is
of the third Wheels okay I'm sure you
won't take that literally I'm just
trying to give it I'm just trying to
give an illustration of how the third
turny of the wheel was
there's a danger that you will be
quoting me later uh and they'll say
what's the third turn the wheel you said
well GUI to R and said uh the first 10
pages of question and 20 Pages answer
it's just 30 pages that's a
whole I don't want you quoting me like
that oh yeah that's
really